<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Running on LinuxUK</title>
    <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/tags/running/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Running on LinuxUK</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jamie Bennett</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 20:44:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.linuxuk.org/tags/running/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheddar Half Marathon and Broadlands 10 Miler</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/cheddar_half_and_broadlands_10miler/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 20:44:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/cheddar_half_and_broadlands_10miler/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=“center” src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/broadlands.jpg&#34;&gt;
A bit belated but here is a short report of two events I ran over the last month or so: the Keynsham 10 Miler and the Cheddar Gorge Half Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keynsham-10-miler-10-miles-16-1-km:1c9cbdac9248dc68976d8b0e1965a3f4&#34;&gt;Keynsham 10 Miler (10 miles, 16.1 km)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event was held on Sunday 22nd May in, you guessed it, Keynsham. The weather was fine although it had been raining the previous days which mean the largely undulating and off-road run was, muddy. Billed as a &amp;ldquo;multi-terrain&amp;rdquo; event the run took us down step and slippy hills (I clearly wore the wrong footware), over decrepit wooden styles, through long grass, up grueling inclines, and over foot-destroying loose stones; and then you do it again (its a two lap course). It was great. I must admit that due to a shoulder injury I picked up running trails in Salt Lake City my fitness has completely plummeted so this challenging off-road 10 miler took more out of me than I expected. Towards the 8 mile mark I was experiencing hamstring craps and at the end the pace slowed to a crawl. Despite all this I posted a respectable time and I will definitely be back again next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cheddar-gorge-half-marathon-13-1-miles-21-1km:1c9cbdac9248dc68976d8b0e1965a3f4&#34;&gt;Cheddar Gorge Half Marathon (13.1 miles, 21.1km)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second time I&amp;rsquo;d ran in Cheddar this year, the first was for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160410_cheddar_gorge_10k/&#34;&gt;10km event&lt;/a&gt;, and again the event was run to perfection. Tom and the team do an admirable job of ensuring the runners are registered quickly, drop their bags of easily, and are on the start line vaguely knowing where they are going. But the main actor in this event is the stunning scenery. Up on the top of Cheddar Gorge you get a great view of the surroundings and a glimpse of the pain to come. I started my Garmin on the walk to the start line this time and my watch read 528ft climbed, which is more than most complete marathons, and this was before the run itself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again the run was off-road, challenging, and &amp;ldquo;undulating&amp;rdquo;, but this time it was also cold, wet, and extremely muddy. Coupled with the lack of training this was probably my most challenging run this year. I took it easy on the first lap but with a 500ft climb in the middle, everything after that, whether it be flat, decline, or incline, gave my legs a bashing. A disappointing time (I was aiming for sub 2hrs and missed it) but a great day so overall a success. I&amp;rsquo;ll be back again in a few weeks to complete the Cheddar Gorge challenge and look forward to running many more &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.relishrunningraces.com&#34;&gt;Relish Running&lt;/a&gt; events next year.
&lt;img align=“center” src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/cheddar_broadlands_medals.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pensford 10k</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160424_pensford10k/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 21:13:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160424_pensford10k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/pensford_medal.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week, another race, this time the Pensford 10k event, but lets take a little step back first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of my &amp;lsquo;racing&amp;rsquo; (very loose term for official events) calendar selection I had the aim of adding at least one, preferably two events per month to ensure that the pressure to line up against others kept me honest and provided the motivation to get my backside off the couch and training. When the event is close by and offers an &amp;ldquo;undulating, and seldom flat course&amp;rdquo; with a nice 50m and 100m steep climb in the middle, it is worth a try, and try I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Race day I lined up with nearly 200 other people, but amongst the normal pre-race banter I was hearing whispers from the more experienced runners: &amp;lsquo;it only gets going around the 5k mark, watch out&amp;rsquo;, and &amp;lsquo;the hill in the middle is a killer&amp;rsquo;. With this in mind, I moved myself from the 40min+ starting group to the 50min+ group all whilst I was wondering what I had gotten myself in to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set off at a slow but steady pace, trying to conserve energy for &amp;lsquo;the hills&amp;rsquo; although at this point I was overtaking people in the faster group which had me a little worried. Despite a few hills the first 5k was fine, up, down, up, down, and up again but rather doable. Then the 5k marker appeared and right on cue, the hill that was the focus of many a conversation at the start of the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a 100m climb sounds rather small, and on paper it is, but when you are trying for a good race time, with tired legs, a dislocated shoulder (did I mention that?) and enjoying the best the South West has to offer you in terms of windy, cold weather, the start of this tiny little hill was not welcome. I&amp;rsquo;d set my Garmin watch to alert me when I was slower than an 8:30 pace thinking me and the beep were never going to meet but unfortunately the slow beep was my unwelcome companion the whole time I climbed this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a slow time (51:27) I really did enjoy it. I am confident I could knock a large chunk of time off that next time, in good health, and with next year being the 30th anniversary of the race, I think I will be back to prove that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next on the agenda, the Keynsham 10 miler but I am sorely tempted to add the Bath Ultra Marathon in September to the list, after all, I&amp;rsquo;m still looking for races.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running the Cheddar Gorge 10k</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160410_cheddar_gorge_10k/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 20:11:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160410_cheddar_gorge_10k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/cheddar_10k1.jpg&#34;&gt;
This week I ran the 2016 inaugural Cheddar Gorge Challenge event, the 10k race. Billed as a &amp;lsquo;lumpy course&amp;rsquo; these series of runs offer &amp;ldquo;more climbing just getting to the start than you will in most other events&amp;rdquo;. With the affectionately named Hell Steps towards the end this is a tough run but more importantly, it is a fun event. Cheddar is beautiful, steeped in history and picturesque from the bottom of the gorge let alone from running up and down it so the prospect of completing 3 races (10k, half marathon, and marathon) in and around the area was too enticing to pass up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/cheddar_10k2.jpg&#34;&gt;
The terrain, according to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.relishrunningraces.com/cheddar-gorge-challenge.php&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;steep in places and very steep everywhere else&amp;rdquo; which sets the scene but to be honest I arrived at the event fully trained but expecting the worse. In reality there were hard sections, easy sections, a little doubt that I could actually complete the event around the 5k mark, and a &amp;lsquo;this is great&amp;rsquo; moment around 7k. The distance is tiny compared to the training I have done but it was a combination of the race-day &amp;lsquo;too fast start pace&amp;rsquo; and the lumpiness that hit my tired legs hard. There was never a time that I truly wanted to give up but there were times when I thought about a brisk walk rather than running. Overall I am happy to say that even up the Hell Steps I broke into a run and completed the course in a not impressive, but rewarding &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strava.com/activities/541134242&#34;&gt;58:28&lt;/a&gt;. I quietly wanted a sub-1hr finish but given the course I was a little sceptical about that but even though the wind was against us most of the race (how does it constantly blow directly at you regardless of your orientation?) I hit my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/cheddar_10k3.jpg&#34;&gt;
So why would I put my body through this I hear you ask. Well, this year I am doing something out of my comfort zone, something a little crazy (for me), and something that I hope will make a difference to others. This year I am running, a lot, and for a good reason. This year I am running to raise money for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macmillan.org.uk/&#34;&gt;MacMillan Cancer Support&lt;/a&gt;. To read about my story please click the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.justgiving.com/JamieBennettRuns&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; which is also where you can donate to this very worthy cause. I am putting myself through several challenges, including a marathon in the Himalayas of Nepal and a 45 mile Ultra Marathon because there are people out there who just can&amp;rsquo;t, so lets together make their lives a little easier during a really hard time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you can, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.justgiving.com/JamieBennettRuns&#34;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running in Nepal</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160221_running_in_nepal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2016 17:58:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160221_running_in_nepal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/nepal_guide_kindle.png&#34; title=&#34;Lonely Planet Guide to Nepal&#34;&gt;
Nepal is such a wonderful place. Steeped in history and culture with some of the most breath-taking sights to be seen, Nepal is the home to Buddhism, the Himalayas, and of course the mighty Mt Everest. Despite all this wealth, the country and the people themselves face a lot of challenges. Economically Nepal is considered a third-world country with many people in utter poverty. To compound this hardship, Nepal has also experienced terrible earthquakes that have left many dead and even more without basic needs such as accommodation, access to food and clean water, and education. Last years earthquakes were terrible and it &lt;a href=&#34;http://earthquaketrack.com/p/nepal/recent&#34;&gt;continues to happen&lt;/a&gt;. This had me thinking, wouldn’t it be great if I could do something, no matter how small, to help out in some way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my love of running I got to learn about the Impact series of Marathons and right there as the inaugural run was &lt;a href=&#34;http://nepalmarathon.co.uk&#34;&gt;Nepal&lt;/a&gt;. Impact Marathons has lofty goals, in fact they are aiming to contribute to the 17 UN Global Goals through running. &lt;em&gt;“Our runners will truly see the impact of their time, money and resources by visiting and meeting all of the projects they are supporting”&lt;/em&gt;. As part of the week long trip we will be helping repair a school that was badly affected by the earthquake as well as undertaking other community projects. The actually marathon will be at the end of the week and promises to combine stunning views, up to 2300m of altitude, and 26.2 miles of running for a great cause. I am really looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I am hoping to complete several new challenges and up my running to ultra distances. At the moment, Nepal is my final planned race of the year but between now and then there is a lot of training to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parkrun</title>
      <link>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160123_parkrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 14:03:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.linuxuk.org/post/20160123_parkrun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;centre&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/running-mud.png&#34; title=&#34;A wet and muddy Park Run&#34;&gt;
I have a confession to make. While I have publicly supported the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.parkrun.com/&#34;&gt;parkrun&lt;/a&gt; initiative for some time and I wholeheartedly believe it is a great idea, I have never actually ran one myself. There have been many excuses from family conflicts at the weekends to blaming the weather but this week I thought I would actually ignore all of this and partake in the spectacle. I chose the closest event, which for me was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.parkrun.org.uk/southwickcountrypark/course/&#34;&gt;Southwick Country Park&lt;/a&gt; in Trowbridge and arrived before the customary 9am start time. Nearly 300 people turned up to run the wet and muddy course and despite not knowing anything about the logistics of Park Run (you pick up a finishing token at the end and have that scanned with your personal parkrun barcode) I mingled into the crowd ready to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course itself was great. 3 laps around a semi-gravelled path with some sections completely covered by 6 inches of rain water. The first lap around I tried to avoid the water but this this only pushed you onto the slippery surrounding mud so for lap 2 and 3 it became obvious that the best option was to just get your feet wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not manage any personal bests but that was not the point; the event itself was great fun and the volunteers were excellent. This may have been my first parkrun but it is definitely not my last, I will be there again this Saturday, 9am, ready to do it all again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&#34;centre&#34; src=&#34;http://www.linuxuk.org/media/park-run-southwick.png&#34; title=&#34;Southwick Park Run&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>